<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Digital Edition of the 1637 Spanish translation of Thomas More's Utopia</title>
            <editor> M.ª Inmaculada Ureña Asensio</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Encoding Chapter 1 for my thesis dissertation</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The bibliographical resources are:
               Utopia de Thomas Moro (1637) translated by Gerónimo de Medinilla. 
               The Utopia of Sir Thomas More (1895) edited by Joseph Lupton. Bilingual edition (Latin and sixteenth-century English translation)</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="header">
              <div type="facsimile" xml:lang="Spanish"> 
                  <head>RELACION, QVE HIZO
                  Rafael Hithlodeo, excelẽte varõ,
                  del felice eſtado dela republica de
                  VTOPIA, ordenada por Thomas
                  Moro, Vizcõde, Ciudadano de la
                  inſigne Ciudad de Lon-
                  dres en Inglaterra.</head></div> 
              <div type="modernization" xml:lang="Spanish"> 
                 <head>Relación que hizo Rafael Hithlodeo, excelente varón, del feliz
                 estado de la república de Utopia, ordenada por Thomas Moro, vizconde, ciudadano de
                 la insigne ciudad de Londres en Inglaterra.</head></div>
              <div type="original" xml:lang="Latin"> 
                 <head>SERMONIS QVEM RAPHAEL HYTHLODAEVS DE OPTI MO REIP. STATV HABVIT, LI
               BER SECVNDVS, PER THO MAM MORVM CIVEM ET VICECOMITEM LONDINENSEM.</head></div>
               <div type="translation" xml:lang="English"> 
                   <head type="title">
                   The second Boke of the communication of Raphael Hythlodaye,
                   concernyng the best state of a common wealthe: con- teynyng the
                   discription of Vtopia, with a large declaration of the Godly
                   gouernement, and of all the good lawes and orders of the same
                   Ilande. </head>  </div>
            </div>
              <div type="Chapter" n="1">
            <div type="title">
               <div type="facsimile" xml:lang="Spanish"> 
                  <head>DESCRIPCION DE LA ISLA. Cap. I</head></div> 
               <div type="modernization" xml:lang="Spanish"> 
                  <head>Descripción de la isla. Capítulo I </head></div>
               <div type="original" xml:lang="Latin"> <head><!-- No title --></head></div>
               <div type="translation"> 
                  <head type="title" xml:lang="English"> <!-- No title --> </head>
               </div>
            </div>  
            <div type="text">
               <div type="facsimile" xml:lang="Spanish"> 
                  <ab> <seg n="1.1"> <!-- double division? --> La Isla de los Vtopienſes, en el medio ſe eſtiẽnde a docientos mil
                     paſſos, i por larguiſsimo eſpacio no ſe eſtrecha conſiderablement; mas
                     al fin de entrambos aidos cabos ſe va enſangoſtando: i eſtas puntas en
                     circunferẽcia de cinquenta mil paſſos, dexan la Isla en forma de Luna
                     nueva. Eſtas extremidades convatidas del mar ſe hallan diſtantes la una de la otra otros onze mil;
                     i el mar defendido de los vientos. </seg> </ab></div> 
               <div type="modernization" xml:lang="Spanish"> 
                  <ab> <seg n="1.1"> La Isla de los Utopienses en el medio se extiende a doscientos mil
                     pasos, y por larguísimo espacio no se estrecha considerablemente; mas al fin de entre ambos cabos se va ensangostando, 
                     y estas puntas en circunferencia de cincuenta mil pasos dejan la Isla en formade Luna nueva.Estas extremidades combatidas del mar se hallan distantes la una de la
                     otra otros once mil y el mar defendido de los vientos. </seg> </ab></div>
               <div type="original" xml:lang="Latin"> <ab>VTOPIENSIVM INSVLA in media sui parte (nam hac latissima est) millia passuum
                  ducenta porrigitur, magnumque per insulae spatium non multo angustior, fines
                  uersus paulatim utrinque tenuatur. hi uelut circunducti circinoquingentorum ambitu millium, insulam totam in lunae speciem renascentis effigiant. 
                  Cuius cornua fretum interfluens millibus passuum plus minus undecim dirimit ac per ingens inane diffusum, circumiectu undique terrae prohibitis uentis, uasti in morem lacus,
                  stagnans magis quam saeuiens,</ab></div>
               <div type="translation"> 
                  <ab type="ab"> he Ilande of Vtopia conteyneth in breadthe in the myddell
                     part of it (for there it is brodest) CC. miles. Whiche bredthe continueth through
                     the moste parte of the Iande, sauyng that by lytle and lytle it commeth in and waxeth narrower towardes both the endes.
                     Betwene thys two corners the sea runneth in, diuydyng them a sonder by the
                     distaunce of .xi. miles or there aboutes, and there surmounteth into a large and wyde</ab></div>
            </div>
         </div>        
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
