<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<?xml-model href="Schema%20Utopia.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
     <!-- essential -->
      <fileDesc>
         <!-- essential -->
         <titleStmt>
            <!-- essential -->
            <title>A Digital Edition of the 1637 Spanish translation of Thomas More's Utopia</title>
            <editor> M.ª Inmaculada Ureña Asensio</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <!-- essential -->
         <publicationStmt>
            <!-- essential -->
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <!-- essential -->
         <sourceDesc>
            <!-- essential -->
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
         <div type="Chapter" n="1">
            <head type="title">
               <pb/>
               <!-- Lupton 1985 p. 115 -->
               <lb/>The second <lb/>Boke of the communication <lb/>of Raphael Hythlodaye,
               concernyng <lb/>the best state of a common wealthe: con- <lb/>teynyng the
               discription of Vtopia, <lb/>with a large declaration of the <lb/>Godly
               gouernement, and of <lb/>all the good lawes and <lb/>orders of the same
               <lb/>Ilande. </head>
            <head type="chapter"> *No title* </head>
            <pb n="115"/>
            <p>
               <!-- PARAGRAPHS --> The Ilande of Vtopia conteyneth in breadthe in the myddell
               part of it (for there it is brodest) CC. miles. Whiche bredthe continueth through
               the moste parte of the Iande, sauyng that by lytle and lytle it commeth in and <pb
                  n="116"/>
               <!-- PARAGRAPHS  --> waxeth narrower towardes both the endes. Whiche fetch- ynge
               about a circuite or compasse of .v.c. myles, do fas- sion the hole Ilande lyke to
               the newe mone. Betwene thys two corners the sea runneth in, diuydyng them a sonder
               by the distaunce of .xi. miles or there aboutes, and there surmounteth into a
               large and wyde sea 3, which, by reason that the Iande of euery syde compasseth it
               about, and shiltreth it from the windes, is not rough nor mountith not with great
               waues, but almost floweth quietlye, not muche vnlike a great standing powle ; and
               maketh almoste al the space within the bellye of the Iande in maner of a hauen;
               and to the great commoditie of the Inhabitauntes receaueth in shyppes towardes
               euery parte of the lande. The forefrontes or frontiers of the .ii. corners, what
               wythe fordys and shelues, and what with rockes, be very ieoperd- ous and
               daungerous. In the middel distaunce betwene <pb n="117"/> them both standeth vp
               aboue the water a great rocke, which therfore is nothing perillous bicause it is
               in sight. Vpon the top of this rocke is a faire and a strong towre builded, which
               thei holde with a garison of men. Other rockes ther be, that lye • hidde vnder the
               water, and b therefore be daungerous. The channelles be knowen onely to
               themselfes. An 1 therfore it seldome chaunceth that any straunger, oneles he be
               guided by a Vtopian, can come in to this hauen. In so muche that they themselfes
               could skaselie entre without ieoperdie, but that their way is directed and ruled
               by certaine Iande markes standing on the shore. By turning, translatynge 2, and
               remouinge this markes into other places, they maye destroye their enemies nauies,
               be thei neuer so many 1• ·The out side ofo the Iande is also full of hauens; but
               the landing is so surely <pb n="118"/> defenced •, what by nature and what by
               workmanshyp of mans hande, that a fewe defenders maye dryue backe many armies. </p>
            <p> Howbeit, as they saye, and as the fassion of the place it selfe doth partely
               shewe, it was not euer compassed about with the sea. But kyng Vtopus, whose name
               as con· querour the Iland beereth (for before that b tyme it was called Abraxa 1),
               which also brought the rude and wild people to that excellent perfection, in al
               good fassions, humanitie, and ciuile gentilnes, wherin they now go be· yond al the
               people of the world ; euen at his first arriuinge and enteringe vpon the lande,
               furth with obteynynge the victory caused .xv. myles space of vplandyshe grounde,
               where the sea had no passage, to be cut and dygged vp ; and so brought the sea
               rounde aboute the lande. He set to thys worke not only the inhabitauntes of the
               Ilande (because they should not thynke it done in contumelye and <pb n="119"/>
               despyte), but also all hys owne soldiours. Thus the worke, beyng diuyded into so
               great a numbre of workemen, was with exceding maruelous spede dyspatched. In so
               muche that the borderers, whiche at the fyrst began to mocke and to gieste at thys
               vayne enterpryse, then turned theyr laughter to marueyle at the successe, and to
               feare. </p>
            <p> There be in the Ilande .liiii.1 large and faire cities or shiere townes, agreyng
               all together in one tonge, in lyke maners, institucions, and Iawes. They be all
               set and situate a lyke, and in all poyntes fashioned a lyke, as farfurth as the
               place or plotte suffereth. Of thies cyties they that be nighest together be
               xxiiii. myles a sonder. Again there is none of them distaunt from the next aboue
               one dayes iorneye a fote. </p>
            <p> There cum yearly to Amaurote out of euery cytie .iii. olde men, wyse and well
               experienced, there to entreate and <pb n="120"/> debate of the common matters of
               the Iande. For thys cytie (because it standeth iust in the myddes of the Ilande,
               and is therfore moste mete for the embassadours of all partes of the realme) is
               taken for the chiefe and head cytie. The precinctes and boundes of the shieres be
               so commodiously appoynted out, and set furth for the cyties, that neuer a one a of
               them all hath of any~ syde lesse then xx. myles of grounde, and of som syde also
               muche more 1, as of that part where the cyties be of farther distaunce a sonder.
               None of the cities desire to enlarge the boundes and lymites of their shieres 1•
               For they count them selfes rather the good husbandes, then the owners of their
               landes. </p>
            </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
